Well, my friends, and welcome to exercise the number 94 in this exercise, we are going to create
and implement the selection salt algorithm in Java.
So the selection sort algorithms start by finding the minimum in every iteration, the minimum value
between the elements of that order in every iteration and put it in the left and the outermost left
section and the start every time iteration, finding the minimum and putting it to the left.
So let's start making this algorithm in Java.
We go to the project select source.
Inside the algorithm package, I will create a new Java class called Selection Soft.
OK.
You can find all of these exercises and all this source codes that we have created in the previous exercises
underneath every project, every exercise resources folder on our Udemy course.
OK, so this is our selection sort of class.
We start by creating public void, the sort that selection sort of selection sorting.
I will take into the perimeter, the array that we are going to search.
So.
This is the algorithm we start by finding and equal to every thought length and one by one move boundary
of unsorted suburb.
So the first step is one iterating through the them the boundary of unsorted substrates.
So one by one move boundary of unsorted submarines
making the four of the forward loop that starts by equal to zero i.e. less then and minus one and a
plus plus OK.
And we find that the minimum the second step is find that minimal element in sorted out a
faint minimum by the X minimum and X equal to.
And we start by making that inner loop.
So in the J equal to I +1 because we consider I is that we have in the first iteration, it's equal
to zero.
We don't have any unsorted addresses and on unsorted or sorted, fully sorted members, so are equal
So we start from j equal to what?
This is the algorithm, because we consider the left is fully sort and we start start again and again
and again, we increase AI every time by one.
So if we are on the iteration number five so equal to five, then GE will start from AI from AI +1,
which is six.
So because we have sorted the previous five numbers game, we this is what this thing we have lectured
at in the animation and we have please go back to the animation with this look selection sort of algorithm
definition and animation, and please learn about it in order to understand what we are doing.
So J less than 10 and J a plus a plus.
So here J Plus plus OK, we start f if out of the at index j less than array at index minimum minimum
index here minimum idea x, then we make the minimum index equal to J.
OK.
This is very simple.
We are going to check if it is not the minimum and make it now the third step is swapping, swapping
the found
minimum
with.
First element in Sudbury.
So what we need to make and temp equal to entry at minimum and here is the minimum index, and we make
only at minimum index equal to array at index I, we are sweeping the elements by making them pretty
valid.
Or we can make a method that that is called the square that make this function.
OK.
So you can make this as a function or you can write it directly as hardcoded code.
No, we have finished that algorithm.
Now let's preempt the other day.
So public void.
Brent Saturday, we took into the part of that late that we needed to print and everything
and and and equal to have a claim for high and equal to zero by less than an eye plus plus time zone
system that out dot, print and or a print of a appendix.
I lost this, OK?
Then outside when we finished, we make system out to print a new line.
Now we need a driver code to test the above algorithm.
So we start by making public static void main.
And this thing args
selections or we make an object from the selection so class that we have created and ends as they equal
to this story that we are going to sort.
OK.
And selection for the selection, sorting for that, a.
Let's pretend it's
sort sorted at way here and selection sorting that, Trent added.
OK, so what we have done here, we created the array.
We have called the method selection sorting that will sort the array with displays sorted today.
My message and selection sorting, printing that array that we have sorted.
OK, back to the algorithm we have created.
The outer loop are equal to zero time and minus one and I press plus that will look through all the
elements from zero to and minus one.
And we created the minimum index, and every time we find them index their minimum element in unsorted
array by making a nested loop and changing it, swapping the founded minimum.
If we have found the minimum as a minimum element between the remaining elements and we swap that.
OK.
This is for printing and let's run and see our code.
This is the array that we are going to sort.
And this is the sort that added a one seven, 12, one, three, three, four and six and everything
is working fine.
So we have congratulations.
We have implemented that selection sort an algorithm inside Java.
And by the way, this this time complexity for this election source is all due and square that we have
talked about much in the previous videos and because we have nested loop.
So this nested loop is on the square, and every time we called, this method will go through and nested
loop on the square and the space complexity.
This is time and this is space complexity.
It is of why.
The good thing about selection sort is it never makes more than all of the swabs and can be useful in
memory.
Right.
It is a costly operation.
OK.
So this is for base and memory efficient.
OK, so use the selection sort in when you have, like a shortage in memory or you have.